{"tossups": [{"question": "A 5 km thick layer of nonionized sodium exists in this layer, which creates a night glow through D-line emissions. Collapse of internal gravity waves in this layer is a primary driving force of global circulation. Near the poles, ice crystals condense to form bluish noctilucent clouds in this layer. Sounding rockets are the primary means of studying this layer, which is inaccessible to planes or satellites. This layer reverses the temperature inversion of the layer beneath, meaning that its temperature (*) decreases with increasing height. In addition to being the coldest layer of the atmosphere, this layer is also where meteors burn up. For 10 points, name this layer of the atmosphere which is located between the stratosphere and thermosphere.", "answer": "mesosphere", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>mesosphere</u></b>", "acceptable": ["mesosphere", "mesosphere"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "2. The leader of one revolt of these people wrote correspondences found in the Cave of Letters. One chronicler of these people wrote the polemic Against Apion. One revolt of these people was led by Lukuas and was crushed by Lucius Quietus. Another revolt of these people was triggered by a city being renamed Aelia Capitolina and was led by a person dubbed (*) \"Son of the Star.\" The first revolt of these people ended with nine hundred Zealots committing suicide in the fortress of Masada. That event was chronicled by Flavius Josephus and preceded an uprising led by Bar Kochba, whose defeat by Hadrian's forces is mourned on Tisha B'Av. For 10 points, name these people who lived in a Roman province with capital at Jerusalem.", "answer": "Jews [accept equivalents]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jews</u></b> [accept equivalents]", "acceptable": ["Jews", "Jews"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man's feats include drinking four draughts of wine at breakfast and eating two whole partridges in front of a sick person with no appetite. This employer of the servant Laurent comments in one scene that a woman should cover her bosom with a handkerchief. Mr. Loyal helps this man by reading an eviction notice. This man takes a box of incriminating (*) letters left by Argas, which is eventually turned over to an officer of the all-seeing King, and is earlier spied on from behind a curtain by Damis [\"dah-MEE\"], who catches him seducing Elmire. In the play in which he appears, Orgon is nearly tricked into giving up his estate to this man. For 10 points, name this hypocritical faux-pious con-man who titles a Moliere comedy.", "answer": "Tartuffe [accept Tartuffe, or the Impostor or Tartuffe, ou l'Imposteur]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tartuffe</u></b> [accept <b><u>Tartuffe,</u></b> or the <b><u>Impostor</u></b> or <b><u>Tartuffe, ou l'Imposteur</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Tartuffe", "Tartuffe", "Tartuffe,", "Impostor", "Tartuffe, ou l'Imposteur"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Some scholars have argued that one depiction of this person is instead a depiction of Mercury and Argo because of the petasus hat he wears; in that same sculpture, a feathered wing slides up this man's right leg. This figure wears a skirt and a leather jerkin and holds a dagger in a Verrocchio sculpture commissioned by Lorenzeo de'Medici. One sculpture of this man has him standing over his shed armor and (*) about to perform his most famous action. This figure is depicted with long curly hair and wears only boots in a free-standing nude statue in bronze by Donatello. Bernini depicted him crouching with a slingshot. For 10 points, name this Biblical figure often depicted standing near the head of Goliath.", "answer": "David", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>David</u></b>", "acceptable": ["David", "David"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In 2004, 30 scientists were held hostage in this archipelago by fisherman who demanded the right to use more efficient fishing methods. These islands were removed from UNESCO's danger list in 2010 because of lobbying from Rafael Correa. Fernandina is the most volcanically active of these islands, which are governed from the capital of Puerto Baquerizo Moreno on (*) San Cristobal. The island of Isabela here, which lies on the Equator, is home to an endemic species of penguin as well as giant tortoises and marine iguanas. Many varieties of finch are also associated with, for 10 points, what Ecuadorean island group visited by Charles Darwin?", "answer": "Galapagos Islands", "category": "Geography", "subcategory": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Galapagos</u></b> Islands", "acceptable": ["Galapagos Islands", "Galapagos"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A rival of this figure once climbed up a peak and hurled a large rock at him, which splintered and made this figure's foot bleed. This man summoned his followers to a lake, held up a certain object without saying a word, and was met with a smile and a laugh by his successor. His mother, Maya, had a vision of a beautiful elephant entering her womb. This man traveled to a deer park to begin his teachings and is considered to be the first (*) arhat. In his adolescence, this deliverer of the \"Flower Sermon\" was disturbed by the sight of an old man, a diseased man, and a corpse. This prompted him to meditate under a Bodhi tree and come up with the Four Noble Truths. For 10 points, name this religious figure who was born Siddhartha Gautama.", "answer": "Buddha [or Siddhartha Gautama before mention]", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Buddha</u></b> [or <b><u>Siddhartha Gautama</u></b> before mention]", "acceptable": ["Buddha", "Buddha", "Siddhartha Gautama"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This author described the \"pivot of heels and knees!\" in a poem whose speaker claims to be \"the arrow, the dew that flies\" while riding on horseback towards the rising sun. She compared herself to a \"pure gold baby that melts to a shriek\" in a poem that begins \"I have done it again, one year in every ten\" and ends \"Out of the ash I rise with my red hair, and I eat men like air\". In another of her poems, the image of a \"man in black with a (*) Meinkampf look\" represents her husband, Ted Hughes. That poem opens with the line \"You do not do, you do not do\" and tells the title figure \"you bastard, I'm through.\" For 10 points, name this poet of \"Ariel\", \"Lady Lazarus\" and \"Daddy\", whose only novel The Bell Jar was published shortly before her 1963 suicide.", "answer": "Sylvia Plath", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sylvia Plath</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sylvia Plath", "Sylvia Plath"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Syntheses of molecules with this property often employ auxiliaries via asymmetric induction. The fact that Mosher's acid has this property allows it to be used as a derivatizing agent to change the NMR shift of other molecules with this property. Meso compounds notably do not have this property due to a plane of symmetry, and it was first studied in crystals of tartaric acid by Louis Pasteur. Molecules with this property are labeled as R or S using the (*) Cahn-Ingold-Prelog rules. Molecules with this property rotate plane polarized light, meaning they are optically active. For 10 points, name this property of some molecules which makes them distinct from their mirror images, which can be roughly defined as handedness.", "answer": "chirality [accept word forms; accept things like they have a chiral center; accept word forms of optical activity until mention, prompt after; prompt on \"stereochemistry\" or word forms; prompt on \"stereoisomers\" or word forms; prompt on \"enantiomers\", \"diasteromers\", \"epimers\", \"anomers\" or word forms]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>chirality</u></b> [accept word forms; accept <b><u>things like they have a chiral center</u></b>; accept <b><u>word forms of optical activity</u></b> until mention, prompt after; prompt on <u>stereochemistry</u> or word forms; prompt on <u>stereoisomers</u> or word forms; prompt on <u>enantiomers\", \"diasteromers\", \"epimers\", \"anomers</u> or word forms]", "acceptable": ["chirality", "chirality", "things like they have a chiral center", "word forms of optical activity"], "promptable": ["stereochemistry", "stereoisomers", "enantiomers\", \"diasteromers\", \"epimers\", \"anomers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man gained national recognition when he gave a speech conceding a closely contested nomination race to Estes Kefauver. His first speech as President called for America to \"bear the burden of a long twilight struggle.\" One initiative of this President was an expansion of Operation Crossroads Africa. Among the accomplishments of his administration was the signing of the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty. On the campaign trail this man hammered home the danger of the (*) \"missile gap.\" The Peace Corps was founded during this man's presidency, and many of his domestic programs were part of his \"New Frontier\" program. He was the first Roman Catholic elected president. For 10 points, name this President who was assassinated in 1963.", "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy [or JFK; prompt on \"Kennedy\"]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Fitzgerald Kennedy</u></b> [or <b><u>JFK</u></b>; prompt on <u>Kennedy</u>]", "acceptable": ["John Fitzgerald Kennedy", "John Fitzgerald Kennedy", "JFK"], "promptable": ["Kennedy"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After being told by a friend that his impulse to defy tradition \"may be from below,\" this man replied \"if I am the Devil's child, I will live then from the Devil.\" This man argued that both abstractionist and materialist traits were possessed by another thinker who spent his whole life wondering \"What do I know?\" He urged people to become \"Man Thinking\" in a work heralded as an \"intellectual Declaration of Independence.\" This author who described Montaigne as a \"Representative Man\" also delivered a speech to the Phi Beta Kappa Society and penned the maxims \"Whoso must be a man, must be a (*) nonconformist\" and \"A foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds.\" For 10 points, name this thinker who delivered \"The American Scholar\" and wrote \"Self-Reliance.\"", "answer": "Ralph Waldo Emerson", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ralph Waldo Emerson</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ralph Waldo Emerson", "Ralph Waldo Emerson"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "11. One minus 19.7 divided by this number is proportional to the Strouhal number, which governs the formation of von Karman streets. For a packed bed, its denominator contains one minus the voidage. One version of this value is the ratio of magnetic advection to magnetic diffusion. It appears on the x-axis of a Moody diagram plotted against the Darcy friction factor. This value can be expressed as the ratio of (*) inertial forces to viscous forces, and is equal to the velocity times length scale divided by kinematic viscosity. At high values of it, eddies and vortices appear in the flow. For 10 points, name this dimensionless parameter which determines whether flow is laminar or turbulent.", "answer": "Reynolds number [or magnetic Reynolds number]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Reynolds</u></b> number [or <b><u>magnetic Reynolds number</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Reynolds number", "Reynolds", "magnetic Reynolds number"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Sir Humphrey Gibbs unsuccessfully tried to dismiss the cabinet of this country. The Byrd Amendment allowed the United States to purchase chromium from this country despite U.N. sanctions. Following the Internal Settlement, control over this country was transferred to men like Abel Muzorewa. The Second Chimurenga (shim-uh-REN-guh) was fought in this country and is often called its (*) \"bush war.\" The government of this nation officially banned political groups like ZAPU and ZANU. This country's 1965 Unilateral Declaration of Independence violated the British principle of \"no independence without majority rule.\" For 10 points, name this erstwhile country ruled by the minority white government of Ian Smith, now known as Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Southern Rhodesia [or Zimbabwe or Zimbabwe Rhodesia before mentioned]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Southern <b><u>Rhodesia</u></b> [or <b><u>Zimbabwe</u></b> or <b><u>Zimbabwe Rhodesia</u></b> before mentioned]", "acceptable": ["Southern Rhodesia", "Rhodesia", "Zimbabwe", "Zimbabwe Rhodesia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One character in this work describes a woman who used to cut up snakes and sell their flesh as fish. Another character in this story is a recently-discharged servant with a pimple on his cheek, who waits for the rain to stop and worries that he will have to become a thief. At the end of this story, the servant kicks an old hag and steals her cloak, leaving her naked, claiming he needs it to survive. The hag had been taking (*) hair off of corpses in the title location in order to make wigs. This story was combined with its author's other story \"In a Grove\" to form the plot of a Kurosawa film. For 10 points, name this story by Ryunosuke Akutagawa, which is set at a namesake gate in Kyoto.", "answer": "\"Rashomon\"", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\"Rashomon\"</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\"Rashomon\"", "\"Rashomon\""], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This composer's second symphony ends with all twelve notes of the chromatic scale played simultaneously. One of his Two Contemplations consists of six increasingly agitated phrases of flute music, which separate seven iterations of an unchanging trumpet melody that ends with a rising inflection. Throughout his symphonies, this composer frequently quoted songs such as \"Columbia, the Gem of the Ocean\" and (*) \"Camptown Races.\" He paid homage to the transcendentalists in his second piano sonata, which is nicknamed \"Concord\". After attending Yale, this modernist supported himself by working as an insurance executive. For 10 points, name this American composer of The Unanswered Question and Three Places in New England.", "answer": "Charles Ives", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "Charles <b><u>Ives</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Charles Ives", "Ives"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A memorable passage in this work describes a family camping trip before asking, \"is this, indeed, the American Genius?\" This text was expanded on in a later tract exploring the widespread \"technostructure\" that prioritizes stasis over efficient risk-taking. This work posits that demand no longer arises \"organically\" from needs but is instead directed by (*) advertising, and dismisses classical economics as irrelevant to a consumer state. This work calls for a renewed public investment, especially in education, after criticizing the \"conventional wisdom\" that no longer applies to post-World War II America. Warning of a widening income disparity within the titular social order, for 10 points, identify this 1958 work by John Galbraith.", "answer": "The Affluent Society", "category": "Social Science", "subcategory": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "The <b><u>Affluent Society</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Affluent Society", "Affluent Society"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This deity was honored at the Ekdysia festival after she turned the daughter of Lamprus and Galatea into a son. After the people of Lycia refused to let her drink from a lake, this goddess turned them into frogs. She was almost raped by a giant who is stretched across several miles in Tartarus, named Tityos. Along with her sister Asteria, this goddess was the daughter of Coeus and Phoebe. She and her lover had sex in the form of quails. For attracting the eye of (*) Zeus, Hera ordered Python to endlessly pursue this figure, who wandered the world until ending up on Delos to give birth. Niobe boasted that her children were more attractive than the children of this goddess. For 10 points, name this goddess, the mother of Apollo and Artemis.", "answer": "Leto", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Leto</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Leto", "Leto"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One artist from this country designed the cover of the first issue of 1893's The Studio and gained fame for his line-block drawings of Salome. Another painter from this nation used historically accurate costumes in his The Finding of the Savior in the Temple and was a compatriot of the artist of candlelit scientific scenes like An (*) Experiment on a Bird in the Air Pump. An Italian-born artist working in this country painted a woman with her eyes closed in Beata Beatrix. An earlier artist born here created Marriage a la Mode and depicted the title figure ending up in Bedlam in his series, A Rake's Progress. For 10 points, name this country home to the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood and William Hogarth.", "answer": "England [or Great Britain; or the United Kingdom; or the U.K.]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>England</u></b> [or <b><u>Great Britain</u></b>; or the <b><u>United Kingdom</u></b>; or the <b><u>U.K.</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["England", "England", "Great Britain", "United Kingdom", "U.K."], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This work's third chapter ends with the line \"The ciborium had come to him\". A girl named Emma inspires one character in it to write a villanelle that repeats the question \"Are you not weary of ardent ways?\" This book's protagonist gets beaten with a cabbage stump by Heron for preferring Byron over Tennyson and discusses Aquinas's theory of beauty with Cranly. In the first section of this novel, Mr. Casey and (*) Dante Riordan argue about the death of Charles Parnell. Its protagonist has an epiphany when he makes eye contact with a solitary girl wading in the sea and is inspired to religiosity by Father Arnall's sermon on hell. It begins with a story involving a \"moocow\" meeting \"baby tuckoo\". For 10 points, name this 1916 novel about Stephen Dedalus by James Joyce.", "answer": "A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "A <b><u>Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</u></b>", "acceptable": ["A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man", "Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A group of Supreme Court cases named for this movement included Stone v. Wisconsin. In a political cartoon about this movement, men take the place of railroad ties underneath tracks, as the \"Consolidation Train\" approaches and a figure \"awakens the sleepers.\" The Anti-Monopolist Party was formed out of this movement by the \"Prince of Cranks,\" Ignatius Donnelly. This movement won a great success in 1876, when Morrison (*) Waite wrote the opinion in the Munn v. Illinois case about grain elevator rates. This movement was founded in Minnesota by a Department of Agriculture employee who wished to modernize Southern farming practices, Oliver Hudson Kelley. For 10 points, name this populist movement which advocated for the interests of farmers.", "answer": "granges [or Granger movement, etc; or Patrons of Husbandry]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>granges</u></b> [or <b><u>Granger movement, etc</u></b>; or <b><u>Patrons of Husbandry</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["granges", "granges", "Granger movement, etc", "Patrons of Husbandry"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One method of detecting this process is Annexin-A5 binding. This process is inhibited by bcl-2, and the binding of the Fas receptor to its ligand is one trigger for it. Another pathway for activating it relies on Apaf-1 binding to cytochrome c released from mitochondria. During it, a chain reaction of caspase activation occurs. During this process, DNA is cleaved into a ladder pattern and the cell membrane forms (*) blebs. Cancer cells are able to evade signals that trigger this this process. C. Elegans undergoes 131 instances of it during development, and it also occurs on the webs between toes during human development. Unlike necrosis, this process is orderly, neat, and a normal cellular function. For 10 points, name this type of programmed cell death.", "answer": "apoptosis [or programmed cell death before mention, prompt on \"cell death\" or \"death\"]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>apoptosis</u></b> [or <b><u>programmed cell death</u></b> before mention, prompt on \"cell death or <b><u>death</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["apoptosis", "apoptosis", "programmed cell death", "death"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The slogan \"4 + 3 = 1\" is used to promote the unification of these people. Soldiers of this ethnicity surrendered to the Italians in the Santona Treason, and a terrorist group associated with these people attacked a nuclear power station at Lemoiz. These people were represented by the now-outlawed (*) Batasuna party. Mark Kurlansky's history of this people traces their control of the cod fishing industry. These people traditionally live between the Ebro and Adour rivers. A group advocating for their independence was erroneously blamed for the 2004 train bombings in Madrid and goes by the name ETA. For 10 points, name this ethnic group, divided between France and Spain, that speaks a language unrelated to any others.", "answer": "Basques [or Vasco; or Vascongado Basque; or Euskaldunak; or Euskotarak; prompt on \"Spanish\" before Spain is mentioned in the giveaway]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Basques</u></b> [or <b><u>Vasco</u></b>; or <b><u>Vascongado Basque</u></b>; or <b><u>Euskaldunak</u></b>; or <b><u>Euskotarak</u></b>; prompt on <u>Spanish\"</u> before Spain is mentioned in the giveaway]", "acceptable": ["Basques", "Basques", "Vasco", "Vascongado Basque", "Euskaldunak", "Euskotarak"], "promptable": ["Spanish\""], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A sentence in one version of this story was described by its author as \"grammar gone to seed\"; that version of this story was \"clawed back into a civilized language once more\" from a French translation found by its author. Its frame narrative is set in a tavern in Angels Camp and involves the narrator's search for a man named Leonidas. The central character of this story once speculated on the fate of Parson Walker's wife and owns a bulldog named (*) Andrew Jackson. Simon Wheeler relates this story's central anecdote, in which a stranger uses some quail shot to win a forty-dollar bet with Jim Smiley, the proud owner of Dan'l Webster. For 10 points, identify this story about a talented amphibian, a work of Mark Twain.", "answer": "\"The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County\" [or \"The Notorious Jumping Frog of Calaveras County\"; or \"Jim Smiley and his Jumping Frog\"; or \"The Jumping Frog\"]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\"The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County\"</u></b> [or <b><u>The Notorious Jumping Frog of Calaveras County</u></b>; or <b><u>Jim Smiley</u></b> or <b><u>his Jumping Frog</u></b>; or <b><u>The Jumping Frog</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["\"The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County\"", "\"The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County\"", "The Notorious Jumping Frog of Calaveras County", "Jim Smiley", "his Jumping Frog", "The Jumping Frog"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "These cells are maintained by the secretion of leukemic inhibitory factor, and one method of creating them involves transfection with SOX2, Klf2, and Oct-4. The transcription factor NANOG is highly regulated by these cells. After forming cylindrical bodies they are grown on a lawn of mitomycin-c and fibroblasts. These cells are missing the checkpoint between G1 and S phases. These cells have a tendency to form teratomas, and are extracted from the inner cell mass of a (*) blastocyst. Therapeutic cloning is a potential application of these cells. These cells are pluripotent, meaning they have the ability to form almost any tissue in the human body. For 10 points, name these cells, which are extracted from human embryos.", "answer": "embryonic stem cells [do NOT accept \"adult stem cells\" at any point; accept IPS or induced pluripotent stem cells before \"inner cell mass\", prompt after]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>embryonic stem cells</u></b> [do NOT accept \"adult stem cells\" at any point; accept <b><u>IPS</u></b> or <b><u>induced pluripotent stem cells</u></b> before \"inner cell mass\", prompt after]", "acceptable": ["embryonic stem cells", "embryonic stem cells", "IPS", "induced pluripotent stem cells"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One section of this work alludes to widespread death by listing \"no trembling harp, no tuned timber, no tumbling hawk\" and \"no swift horse\". A passage about Finn and his sons is another of this work's \"four funerals\", which also include the Lay of the Last Survivor. It is found in Cotton Vitellius A.xv, also known as the Nowell Codex. Its protagonist is twice failed by swords, and is prompted by the death of (*) Aeschere to dive into a reptile-infested lake in search of a descendant of Cain. That protagonist is mortally wounded while fighting a dragon with Wiglaf. Shortly after it begins, its title character arrives at the mead hall of Heorot to assist the Danish king Hrothgar. For 10 points, name this Old English epic about a Geatish hero who kills Grendel.", "answer": "Beowulf", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Beowulf</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Beowulf", "Beowulf"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "The constant appearing in this law was first approximated using a torsion balance by Henry Cavendish and is equal to about 6.67 times 10 to the negative 11th in SI units. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["NEWTON", "TIDE", "LAPLACE"], "parts": ["Identify this law which gives the gravitational attraction between two bodies as proportional to the product of their masses divided by the square of the distance of their centers apart.", "The period of these phenomena can be derived by using Newton's Law of gravitation and considering a system in which the Moon is pulling on a ring of deformable liquid surrounding the earth as it orbit", "A set of differential equations that describe tides are named for this Frenchman. He also names an operation symbolized del squared that equals the sum of the partial second derivatives of a function."], "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answers_formatted": ["<b><u>NEWTON</u></b>", "<b><u>TIDE</u></b>", "<b><u>LAPLACE</u></b>"], "acceptable": [["NEWTON", "NEWTON"], ["TIDE", "TIDE"], ["LAPLACE", "LAPLACE"]], "promptable": [[], [], []], "rejectable": [[], [], []], "metadata": ["", "", ""]}, {"leadin": "Three nude women, including one who is putting on green socks, stand in front of this painting in the artist's later work, The Models. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["LA GRANDE JATTE", "POINTILLISM", "YELLOW/JAUNE"], "parts": ["Identify this painting by a contemporary of Paul Signac whose figures include a man playing a trumpet and four men in white rowing a boat. A man smokes a pipe in the foreground of this work", "0] Georges Seurat's A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte was painted in this style, which composes images from small dots of pure color", "It's not green, but Paul Signac created a pointillist seascape titled for a sail with this color. Van Gogh and Gauguin spent time together in a house of this color on the Place Lamartine, with Van Gogh decorating it with his sunflower paintings."], "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answers_formatted": ["<b><u>LA GRANDE JATTE</u></b>", "<b><u>POINTILLISM</u></b>", "<b><u>YELLOW/JAUNE</u></b>"], "acceptable": [["LA GRANDE JATTE", "LA GRANDE JATTE"], ["POINTILLISM", "POINTILLISM"], ["YELLOW/JAUNE", "YELLOW/JAUNE"]], "promptable": [[], [], []], "rejectable": [[], [], []], "metadata": ["", "", ""]}]}